So have you ever wondered what it would be like
هل تخيلت يوماً كيف قد تكون الحياة
to live in a place with no rules?
في مكان خالٍ من أي قواعد؟
That sounds pretty cool.
شعور رائع بالتأكيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You wake up one morning, however,
لكنك ستستيقظ ذات صباح،
and you discover that the reason there are no rules
لتكتشف أن سبب عدم وجود قواعد
is because there's no government, and there are no laws.
هو لعدم وجود حكومة ولا قوانين.
In fact, all social institutions have disappeared.
في الواقع، جميع المؤسسات الاجتماعية اختفت.
So there's no schools,
فلا يوجد مدارس،
there's no hospitals,
ولا مستشفيات،
there's no police,
ولا شرطة،
there's no banks,
ولا بنوك،
there's no athletic clubs,
ولا نوادي رياضية،
there's no utilities.
ولا خدمات.
Well, I know a little bit about what this is like,
حسناً، أنا أعلم قليلاً طبيعة هذا الشعور،
because when I was a medical student in 1999,
لأني عندما كنت طالبة طب سنة 1999
I worked in a refugee camp in the Balkans during the Kosovo War.
كنت أعمل في معسكرلاجئين في شبه جزيرة البالكان خلال حرب الكوزوفو.
When the war was over,
عندما انتهت الحرب،
I got permission -- unbelievably -- from my medical school
حصلت -- علي غيرالمتوقع -- على تصريح من الجامعة
to take some time off
لأخذ فترة إجازة
and follow some of the families that I had befriended in the camp
لمرافقة بعض العائلات التى أقمت صداقات معهم في المعسكر
back to their village in Kosovo,
إلي قريتهم في كوزوفو،
and understand how they navigated life in this postwar setting.
لكي أفهم كيف يستطيعون التعايش في ظل أوضاع ما بعد الحرب.
Postwar Kosovo was a very interesting place
كوزوفو بعد الحرب كانت مكاناً مشوقاً جداً
because NATO troops were there,
لأن قوات حلف ال(ناتو) كانت هناك،
mostly to make sure the war didn't break out again.
غالباً للتأكد من عدم إندلاع الحرب مرة أخرى.
But other than that, it was actually a lawless place,
لكن عدا ذلك، كان المكان في الواقع بلا قوانين،
and almost every social institution, both public and private,
ومعظم الهيئات الاجتماعية الحكومية والخاصة،
had been destroyed.
دمرت.
So I can tell you
لذلك أستطيع أن أقول لكم
it is absolutely thrilling ...
يمثل ذلك شعوراً مثيراً للغاية
for about 30 minutes,
لمدة حوالي ثلاثين دقيقة،
because that's about how long it takes before you run into a situation
لأن هذه تقريباً هي المدة التي تمر قبل أن تواجه موقفاً
where you realize how incredibly vulnerable you are.
تكتشف من خلاله إلي أي مدى أنت معرض للخطر.
For me, that moment came when I had to cross the first checkpoint,
بالنسبة لي، مررت بهذا الموقف عند إقترابي من أول لجنة تفتيش،
and I realized as I drove up
واستوعبت في طريقي
that I would be negotiating passage through this checkpoint
أنني لأمر من هذه اللجنة سوف أتفاوض
with a heavily armed individual
مع فرد مدجج بالأسلحة
who, if he decided to shoot me right then and there,
والذي إذا ما قرر أن يطلق علي النار في تلك اللحظة وذلك المكان،
actually wouldn't be doing anything illegal.
لن يكون قد ارتكب فعل غير قانوني.
But the sense of vulnerability that I had was absolutely nothing
لكن شعوري بعدم الأمان
in comparison to the vulnerability of the families that I got to know
لا يقارن بنفس الشعور لدى العائلات التي تعرفت عليهم
over that year.
خلال تلك السنة.
You see, life in a society where there are no social institutions
كما ترون، الحياة في مجتمع بدون مؤسسات اجتماعية
is riddled with danger and uncertainty,
مليئة بالمخاطر وعدم اليقين،
and simple questions like, "What are we going to eat tonight?"
و تصبح أسئلة بسيطة مثل: "ماذا سنأكل اليوم؟"
are very complicated to answer.
إجاباتها في غاية التعقيد.
Questions about security, when you don't have any security systems,
أسلئة حول الأمان، في ظل عدم وجود نظام أمني،
are terrifying.
تصبح مخيفة.
Is that altercation I had with the neighbor down the block
هل الجدال الذي حدث ما بيني و بين جاري
going to turn into a violent episode that will end my life
سوف ينقلب إلي واقعة عنف قد تنهي حياتي
or my family's life?
أو حياة عائلتي؟
Health concerns when there is no health system
مخاوف صحية في ظل عدم توفر نظام صحي
are also terrifying.
أيضاً مخيفة.
I listened as many families had to sort through questions like,
لقد استمعت للعديد من العائلات وهم يطرحون أسئلة مثل:
"My infant has a fever. What am I going to do?"
"طفلي حرارته مرتفعة ماذا سوف أفعل؟"
"My sister, who is pregnant, is bleeding. What should I do?
"أختي الحامل تنزف ماذا يجب علي أن افعل؟"
Who should I turn to?"
"لمن ألجأ؟"
"Where are the doctors, where are the nurses?
"أين الأطباء؟ أين الممرضون؟"
If I could find one, are they trustworthy?
"وحتي لو وجدت أيٍ منهم، هل هم أهل للثقة؟"
How will I pay them? In what currency will I pay them?"
"كيف سأدفع لهم؟ وأي عملة سوف استخدم؟"
"If I need medications, where will I find them?
"في حالة احتياجي لعلاج أين سأجده؟"
If I take those medications, are they actually counterfeits?"
"و في حالة أخذي لهم، هل من الممكن أن يكونوا مزيفين؟"
And on and on.
وإلخ.
So for life in these settings,
بالنسبة للحياة في هذه الظروف،
the dominant theme, the dominant feature of life,
يصبح الطابع الغالب عليها،
is the incredible vulnerability that people have to manage
هو شعور الضعف الذي لا يوصف والذي يجب علي الناس مواجهته
day in and day out,
كل يوم،
because of the lack of social systems.
بسبب عدم توفر أنظمة اجتماعية.
And it actually turns out
ولقد اتضح في الواقع
that this feature of life is incredibly difficult to explain
أن هذا الوضع المعيشي من الصعب جداً أن يفسر
and be understood by people who are living outside of it.
ويفهم من قبل الناس الذين يعيشون خارجه.
I discovered this when I left Kosovo.
هذا ما اكتشفته بعدما غادرت كوزوفو.
I came back to Boston, I became a physician,
لقد عدت إلي بوستون، وأصبحت طبيبة،
I became a global public health policy researcher.
أصبحت باحثة عالمية للسياسات الصحية.
I joined the Harvard Medical School
التحقت بكلية الطب بجامعة هارفرد
and Brigham and Women's Hospital Division of Global Health.
ومستشفى بريغهام ومستشفى المرأة شعبة الصحة العالمية.
And I, as a researcher,
و كباحثة،
really wanted to get started on this problem right away.
أردت بشدة أن أبدأ بهذه المشكلة فوراً.
I was like, "How do we reduce the crushing vulnerability
كنت أتسائل، "كيف يمكننا أن نحد من الشعور الساحق بالضعف
of people living in these types of fragile settings?
الذي يشعر به من يعيشون في هذه الأوضاع الحساسة؟
Is there any way we can start to think about
هل من الممكن أن نبدأ بالتفكير
how to protect and quickly recover
في سبل لحماية وسرعة تعافي
the institutions that are critical to survival,
المؤسسات الضرورية للبقاء على قيد الحياة
like the health system?"
كالنظام الصحي؟"
And I have to say, I had amazing colleagues.
و يجب أن أخبركم أني كان لدي زملاء ممتازون.
But one interesting thing about it was,
ولكن الشيء المثير للإنتباه هو
this was sort of an unusual question for them.
أن السؤال كان بالنسبة لهم غير معتاد.
They were kind of like, "Oh, if you work in war,
كانت ردود أفعالهم مثل "أليس العمل في فترة الحرب
doesn't that mean you work on refugee camps,
يتمثل في العمل في معسكرات اللاجئين،
and you work on documenting mass atrocities?" --
وتسجيل الفظائع الجماعية وما إلى ذلك؟" --
which is, by the way, very, very, very important.
والتي هي بالطبع مهام في غاية الضرورة.
So it took me a while to explain why I was so passionate about this issue,
لذلك استغرق مني الأمر بعض الوقت لشرح لماذا كنت متحمسة جدا لهذه المسألة،
until about six years ago.
إلى من حوالي ست سنوات.
That's when this landmark study
وذلك عندما نشرت هذه الدراسة
that looked at and described the public health consequences of war
التي تبحث في وتوصف عواقب الحروب
was published.
علي الصحة العامة.
They came to an incredible, provocative conclusion.
و توصلوا الى استنتاج مثير لا يوصف.
These researchers concluded
فقد خلص هؤلاء الباحثون
that the vast majority of death and disability from war
إلى أن الغالبية العظمى من حالات الموت والعجز بسبب الحرب
happens after the cessation of conflict.
تحدث بعد انتهاء الصراع.
So the most dangerous time to be a person living in a conflict-affected state
لذا فإن الوقت الأكثر خطورة على حياة شخص يعيش في دولة بها قتال
is after the cessation of hostilities;
هي فترة ما بعد توقف القتال؛
it's after the peace deal has been signed.
فترة ما بعد توقيع اتفاقية سلام.
It's when that political solution has been achieved.
ذلك عندما تتوصل الدولة إلى ذلك الحل السياسي.
That seems so puzzling, but of course it's not,
يبدو ذلك كشيءٍ محير ولكنه بالطبع ليس كذلك،
because war kills people by robbing them of their clinics,
لأن الحروب تقتل الناس بسلبها لهم عياداتهم الطبية،
of their hospitals,
و مستشفياتهم،
of their supply chains.
وسلاسل التوريد الخاصة بهم.
Their doctors are targeted, are killed; they're on the run.
أطبائهم يستهدفون، يقتلون؛ إنهم دائماً في حالة هروب.
And more invisible and yet more deadly is the destruction
والأقل وضوحاً لكن الأكثر بشاعةً.
of the health governance institutions and their finances.
هو تدمير مؤسسات الحوكمة الصحية ومواردها المالية.
So this is really not surprising at all to me.
لذلك فهذا الشأن غير مفاجئ إطلاقاً بالنسبة لي.
But what is surprising and somewhat dismaying,
لكن المدهش حقاً و المزعج الى حدٍ ما.
is how little impact this insight has had,
هو التأثير الضعيف لهذه النظرية،
in terms of how we think about human suffering and war.
من حيث رؤيتنا للمعاناة الإنسانية والحروب.
Let me give you a couple examples.
اسمحوا لي أن أطرح عليكم بعض الأمثلة.
Last year, you may remember,
في العام الماضي، قد تتذكرون،
Ebola hit the West African country of Liberia.
هاجم مرض الإيبولا دولة ليبيريا في غرب إفريقيا.
There was a lot of reporting about this group, Doctors Without Borders,
كان هناك كثير من التقارير عن مجموعة أطباء بلا حدود،
sounding the alarm and calling for aid and assistance.
يدقون ناقوس الخطر وينادون لطلب المساعدة والعون.
But not a lot of that reporting answered the question:
ولكن هذه التقارير لم تجب على السؤال على النحو الكافي:
Why is Doctors Without Borders even in Liberia?
لماذا كانت مجموعة أطباء بلا حدود موجودة في ليبيريا؟
Doctors Without Borders is an amazing organization,
مجموعة أطباء بلا حدود هي منظمة رائعة،
dedicated and designed to provide emergency care in war zones.
مخصصة ومصممة لتوفير عناية لحالات الطوارئ في مناطق الحرب.
Liberia's civil war had ended in 2003 --
الحرب الأهلية في ليبيريا كانت قد انتهت في سنة 2003 --
that was 11 years before Ebola even struck.
كان ذلك قبل هجوم مرض الإيبولا بأحد عشر عاماً.
When Ebola struck Liberia,
عندما هاجم الإيبولا ليبيريا،
there were less than 50 doctors in the entire country
كان عدد الأطباء المتواجدين أقل من خمسين طبيباً
of 4.5 million people.
في دولة عدد سكانها 4.5 مليون.
Doctors Without Borders is in Liberia
مجموعة أطباء بلا حدود موجودة في ليبيريا
because Liberia still doesn't really have a functioning health system,
لأن ليبيريا فعلياً لا تزال بلا نظام صحي حقيقي،
11 years later.
حتي بعد أحد عشر عاماً.
When the earthquake hit Haiti in 2010,
في سنة 2010، عندما ضرب الزلزال دولة هايتي،
the outpouring of international aid was phenomenal.
كان تدفق المساعدات العالمية استثنائياً.
But did you know that only two percent of that funding
ولكن هل تعلمون أن فقط 2 في المائة من هذا التمويل
went to rebuild Haitian public institutions,
استخدم لإعادة بناء المؤسسات العامة الهايتية،
including its health sector?
بما في ذلك قطاعها الصحي؟
From that perspective,
من هذا المنطلق،
Haitians continue to die from the earthquake even today.
لا يزال أفراد شعب هايتي يموتون بسبب الزلزال حتى اللآن.
I recently met this gentleman.
التقيت مؤخراً هذا الرجل.
This is Dr. Nezar Ismet.
د. نزارعصمت.
He's the Minister of Health in the northern autonomous region of Iraq,
وزير الصحة فى منطقة الحكم الذاتي الشمالية فى العراق،
in Kurdistan.
في كردستان.
Here he is announcing that in the last nine months,
وهو هنا يعلن أنه في التسعة أشهر الأخيرة،
his country, his region, has increased from four million people
إزداد عدد السكان في بلده ومنطقته من أربعة ملايين
to five million people.
إلى خمسة ملايين مواطن.
That's a 25 percent increase.
بمعدل خمسة وعشرين في المئة.
Thousands of these new arrivals have experienced incredible trauma.
الآلاف من هؤلاء الوافدين الجدد واجهوا أذىً لا يصدق.
His doctors are working 16-hour days without pay.
أطباؤه يعملون 16 ساعة يومياً بدون أجر.
His budget has not increased by 25 percent;
ميزانيته لم تزد بخمسة وعشرين في المئة؛
it has decreased by 20 percent,
بل انخفضت بعشرين في المئة،
as funding has flowed to security concerns and to short-term relief efforts.
مع تدفق التمويل إلى الشئون الأمنية و جهود الإغاثة قصيرة المدي.
When his health sector fails --
عندما يفشل قطاعه الصحي --
and if history is any guide, it will --
والذي سوف يحدث إن اعتبرنا التاريخ دليلاً --
how do you think that's going to influence
ماذا سيكون تأثير ذلك على
the decision making of the five million people in his region
اتخاذ القرار للخمسة مليون شخص الموجودين في المنطقة
as they think about whether they should flee
وهم يتسائلون إذا ما كان يجب أن يفروا هاربين
that type of vulnerable living situation?
من هذه الحياة المعرضة للخطر؟
So as you can see, this is a frustrating topic for me,
لذلك كما ترون، هذا موضوع محبط بالنسبة لي،
and I really try to understand:
وأنا أحاول جاهدةً أن أفهم
Why the reluctance to protect and support
ما هو سبب التردد في حماية ودعم
indigenous health systems and security systems?
النظام الصحي والأمني لسكان المنطقة؟
I usually tier two concerns, two arguments.
عادةً ما أجد نوعين من المخاوف أو وجهات النظر.
The first concern is about corruption,
التخوف الأول يتعلق بالفساد،
and the concern that people in these settings are corrupt
قد تغلب على سلوك الناس في هذه الظروف
and they are untrustworthy.
وغير موثوق فيهم.
And I will admit that I have met unsavory characters
وأنا أعترف أنني قد قابلت أشخاصاً بغضاء
working in health sectors in these situations.
يعملون في القطاعات الصحية في هذه الأحوال.
But I will tell you that the opposite is absolutely true
لكني أريد أن أؤكد لكم أن العكس صحيح تماماً
in every case I have worked on,
في كل الحالات التي عملت عليها،
from Afghanistan to Libya, to Kosovo, to Haiti, to Liberia --
من أفغانستان إلى ليبيا وكوزوفو وهاييتي وليبريا --
I have met inspiring people,
لقد قابلت أشخاصً ملهمين،
who, when the chips were down for their country,
والذين حتى في أسوأ الظروف،
they risked everything to save their health institutions.
كانوا يضحون بكل شيء لكي ينقذوا مؤسسات دولتهم الصحية.
The trick for the outsider who wants to help
لكي يسطيع شخص من خارج هذه المناطق أن يقدم المساعدة
is identifying who those individuals are,
يجب أولاً أن يحدد ويميّز هؤلاء الأفراد،
and building a pathway for them to lead.
وأن يبني لهم مسارً ليسلكوه.
That is exactly what happened in Afghanistan.
ذلك ما حدث بالفعل في أفغانستان.
One of the unsung and untold success stories
إحدى قصص النجاح الغير معروفة
of our nation-building effort in Afghanistan
عن جهودنا في بناء دولة أفغانستان
involved the World Bank in 2002 investing heavily
هي عن الاستثمار المكثف للبنك الدولي سنة 2002
in identifying, training and promoting Afghani health sector leaders.
في تحديد وتدريب وتعزيز قادة القطاع الصحي الأفغاني.
These health sector leaders have pulled off an incredible feat
لقد حقق هؤلاء القادة المعينين إنجازً مذهلاً
in Afghanistan.
في أفغانستان.
They have aggressively increased access to health care
فقد نجحوا في زيادة فرص الحصول على رعاية صحية
for the majority of the population.
لأغلبية الشعب.
They are rapidly improving the health status
إنهم يحسّنون من الحالة الصحية للشعب الأفغاني
of the Afghan population,
بسرعة فائقة،
which used to be the worst in the world.
بعدما كانت الأسوأ في العالم.
In fact, the Afghan Ministry of Health does things
في الواقع، وزارة الصحة الأفغانية تقوم بأشياء
that I wish we would do in America.
أتمنى أن نقوم بها نحن في أمريكا.
They use things like data to make policy.
يستخدمون أشياءً كالبيانات مثلاً لوضع السياسات.
It's incredible.
هذا مذهل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The other concern I hear a lot about is:
أما التخوف الآخر الذي أسمعه كثيراً هو:
"We just can't afford it, we just don't have the money.
"لا نستطيع تحمل ذلك، نحن لا نملك المال الكافي.
It's just unsustainable."
هذا الشيء غير مستدام."
I would submit to you that the current situation
سوف أعترف لكم أن الوضع الحالي
and the current system we have
والنظام القائم لدينا حالياً
is the most expensive, inefficient system we could possibly conceive of.
هو أغلى نظام من الممكن الحصول عليه ومع ذلك الآقل فاعلية.
The current situation is that when governments like the US --
الوضع الحالي هو عندما تكون حكومة مثل الولايات المتحدة --
or, let's say, the collection of governments
ولنقول، مجموعة الحكومات
that make up the European Commission --
التي تكوّن الإتحاد الأوروبي --
every year, they spend 15 billion dollars
تصرف 15 مليار دولار سنوياً
on just humanitarian and emergency and disaster relief worldwide.
علي الإغاثة في الحالات الإنسانية و الطارئة عالمياً.
That's nothing about foreign aid, that's just disaster relief.
وذلك لا يشمل المعونات الأجنبية، فقط إغاثة الكوارث.
Ninety-five percent of it goes to international relief agencies,
خمسة وتسعين في المئة منه يذهب إلى وكالات الإغاثة الدولية،
that then have to import resources into these areas,
والذين بدورهم يستوردون الموارد المطلوبة إلى هذه المناطق،
and knit together some type of temporary health system, let's say,
ثم يكوِّنون منها نوعاً من النظام الصحي المؤقت،
which they then dismantle and send away when they run out of money.
والذي بعدئذ يفكك ويرسل بعيداً عندما ينفذ المال.
So our job, it turns out, is very clear.
لذا فإن عملنا، كما يتضح، مفهوم جداً.
We, as the global health community policy experts,
نحن كخبراء سياسات مجتمع الصحة العالمي،
our first job is to become experts in how to monitor
مهمتنا الأولى هى أن نصبح خبراء في كيفية مراقبة
the strengths and vulnerabilities of health systems
نقاط القوة والضعف في النظم الصحية
in threatened situations.
عند التعرض للخطر.
And that's when we see doctors fleeing,
وذلك حينما نرى الأطباء يفرّون،
when we see health resources drying up,
والموارد الطبية تضمحل،
when we see institutions crumbling --
ونرى المؤسسات تنهار --
that's the emergency.
هذه هي حالة الطوارئ.
That's when we need to sound the alarm and wave our arms.
عندئذ نحتاج إلى دق ناقوس الخطر والتلويح بأذرعنا.
OK?
حسناً؟
Not now.
ليس الآن.
Everyone can see that's an emergency, they don't need us to tell them that.
يمكن للجميع رؤية أن هذه حالة طوارئ، فهم ليسوا بحاجة لنا أن نخبرهم بذلك.
Number two:
رقم إثنين:
places like where I work at Harvard need to take their cue
يجب على الأماكن مثل التي أعمل بها في جامعة هارفرد
from the World Bank experience in Afghanistan,
أن تستفيد من خبرة البنك الدولي في أفغانستان،
and we need to -- and we will --
ونحن بحاجة إلى -- وسوف ننفذ --
build robust platforms to support health sector leaders like these.
بناء برامج نشيطة وقوية لدعم قادة القطاعات الصحية المماثلة.
These people risk their lives.
هؤلاء الناس يخاطرون بحياتهم.
I think we can match their courage with some support.
أعتقد أننا من الممكن أن نكافئ شجاعتهم ببعض الدعم.
Number three:
رقم ثلاثة:
we need to reach out and make new partnerships.
يجب أن نتواصل ونبني شراكات جديدة.
At our global health center,
لقد أطلقنا مبادرة جديدة في
we have launched a new initiative with NATO and other security policy makers
المركز الصحي العالمي بمشاركة حلف الناتو وصناع سياسات أمنية آخرون
to explore with them what they can do to protect health system institutions
بهدف البحث في طرق للمحافظة على مؤسسات النظام الصحي
during deployments.
أثناء عمليات الإنتشار.
We want them to see
نحن نريدهم أن يرون
that protecting health systems and other critical social institutions
أن حماية الأنظمة الصحية والمؤسسات الاجتماعية الأساسية الأخرى
is an integral part of their mission.
جزء لا يتجزأ من مهمتهم.
It's not just about avoiding collateral damage;
لا يتعلق الأمر بمجرد تجنب الدمار المباشر؛
it's about winning the peace.
الهدف الأساسي هو تحقيق السلام.
But the most important partner we need to engage is you,
لكن الشريك الأهم بالنسبة لنا هو أنتم،
the American public, and indeed, the world public.
الجمهور الأمريكي، بل الجمهور العالمي في الحقيقة.
Because unless you understand the value of social institutions,
لأنه ما لم تفهموا قيمة المؤسسات الاجتماعية،
like health systems in these fragile settings,
كالأنظمة الصحية في تلك المواقف الحساسة،
you won't support efforts to save them.
لن تدعموا الجهود التي تسعى لإنقاذها.
You won't click on that article
لن تنقر على الرابط الذي يفتح مقالة تتحدث
that talks about "Hey, all those doctors are on the run in country X.
عن"كل هؤلاء الأطباء الذين يعملون بصفة متواصلة في دولة ما.
I wonder what that means.
وأتساءل ماذا يعني ذلك.
I wonder what that means
أتساءل ماذا يعني ذلك
for that health system's ability to, let's say, detect influenza."
بالنسبة لمقدرة هذا النظام الصحي على دعنا نقول كشف الإنفلونزا."
"Hmm, it's probably not good." That's what I'd tell you.
"إنها ربما ليست جيدة" هذا ما سوف أقوله لكم.
Up on the screen,
لقد وضعت على الشاشة،
I've put up my three favorite American institution defenders and builders.
الأمريكيون الثلاثة المفضلون بالنسبة إلي من المدافعين عن والبنائين للمؤسسات.
Over here is George C. Marshall,
هنا هو جورج س. مارشال،
he was the guy that proposed the Marshall Plan
وهو الرجل الذي اقترح خطة المارشال
to save all of Europe's economic institutions after World War II.
لإنقاذ جميع المؤسسات الإقتصادية بأوروبا بعد الحرب العالمية الثانية.
And this Eleanor Roosevelt.
وهذه أليانور روزفلت.
Her work on human rights really serves as the foundation
عملها في مجال حقوق الإنسان حقاً بمثابة الأساس
for all of our international human rights organizations.
لجميع مؤسسات حقوق الإنسان العالمية.
Then my big favorite is Ben Franklin,
ثم الأكثر تفضيلاً بالنسبة إلي بن فرانكلين،
who did many things in terms of creating institutions,
والذي قام بإنشاء الكثير من المؤسسات،
but was the midwife of our constitution.
ولكنه كان منشئ الدستور الأمريكي.
And I would say to you
وأود أن أقول لكم
that these are folks who, when our country was threatened,
أنه عندما كان وطننا مهدداً بالخطر،
or our world was threatened,
أو كان عالمنا مهدداً بالخطر،
they didn't retreat.
لم يتراجع هؤلاء الأشخاص.
They didn't talk about building walls.
لم يتحدثوا عن بناء الحوائط.
They talked about building institutions to protect human security,
بل تحدثوا عن بناء مؤسسات لحماية الأمن البشري،
for their generation and also for ours.
لجيلهم وأيضاً لجيلنا.
And I think our generation should do the same.
وأنا أعتقد أن جيلنا يجب أن يفعل نفس الشيء.
Thank you.
شكراً.